consider now these two ideas
one
that things in the universe generally
match the way that they are spoken about
in terms of the world at large
they rely on their causes and they rely
on comparison one to the other
two
that they spring up all of a sudden
products of nothing more than mental
pictures and names
these two ideas could never convene
and cooperate with regard to any single
object in the world
if thinking thus we approach the
position that things exist with some
reality
of their own
we would have to assert
that there was no single thing in this
entire universe that depended on
conditions
and then
we'd have to go further and say that
nothing existed at all
cool good good reading it's it's very
difficult i'm sorry uh
the ideas are difficult and the wording
is difficult
but uh
the pension llamas saying
well let's take uh two ideas let's take
these two approaches to the world okay
uh what's the first one
well
let's say that everyone the way people
talk is correct
you know
let's say that the way you see the
internet
on the internet when you read the news
let's say that's all correct
you know
and
the reason things happen
is that economic causes
political causes or
health health
concerns in the world
and these are all these events
and all these forces
in the world
uh political
economic
uh health
these are pushing things you know these
forces
in the world are making things happen
you know
not only that
but happiness itself is a relative thing
you know like uh
if you feel i don't know if if you get
locked up in your house for a year
because of the virus
then
it's so exciting to go to the coffee
shop in sedona
which sunum which closes at
on the on the internet it says they
close at five but they really close at
one
and then last week they start to close
at noon
you know and uh
but still by comparison
uh to sit in your house all day
or to to go out to the coffee shop that
closes at noon
uh
still it's pretty exciting to go you
know
uh before noon
and uh by comparison so the world says
there's two possibilities okay number
one
the internet the news all the
politicians everybody says
there are forces in the world economic
political
uh
the health situation
these are these are causing everything
and
if you feel happy or not it's just by
comparison you know like
before kovind
the sedona coffee shop is one of the
most boring places in the world
but uh after cloven it seems very
exciting you know
and uh look everything's just by
comparison
so that's the way the world talks okay
that's the first possibility now
here's the second possibility
things just happen
when
pictures come out of your karmic suits
okay
that's the whole that's how everything
happens
okay
forget economies
forget politics uh forget health
there's no forces in the world
pushing each other and creating
uh
creating happiness or sadness for big
groups of people
those don't exist at all
the second possibility
is that everything we see
even big things like what countries are
doing
is coming from my own seeds my personal
sins okay i see what i see
i see the world that i see
because of pictures
coming out of my mind okay
so let's say i know i have some nice
watermelon juice
you know
did uh i don't know
did somebody my friends like christina
cassica or vimalus berber
that did they go to the store
and bought some watermelons
and
brought them to the college and i
brought them home you know and i made
watermelon juice is that how i got
watermelon juice
that's the first view
then the second view is uh
i shared
my food
i shared my country's abundance
with the poor countries and and i helped
people in poor countries
i built houses in vietnam
for mr bin's poor people
or
i helped john brady's project to employ
the poor people all over the world to
type the ancient books
and
i put seeds in my mind for watermelon
juice
and then
suddenly they opened this morning and
watermelon juice fill my
glass and i can drink it
now here he says
uh suppose that watermelon juice just
boom spring up
suddenly
how
look they didn't plant watermelons and
christina vimla those guys know they
didn't bring
to the college gals they didn't bring
them with paula didn't drive there
ellie stayed home
you know
that's not how i got the watermelon
they are springing up out of
my seats okay and then it says here
names
what's the role of names gestala you
know i i understand
when you teach about seeds opening in
your mind
i understand you're talking about the
scene splits open
and a picture comes out
and a picture goes to the colors and the
shapes
and the picture makes the watermelon
juice out of red color and the square
shape i understand that
but why they mention names here guess
what why they say
pictures and names and
it's a little confusing okay it's not
that
words are coming out of your mind and
creating things when they say
in
higher middle way and by the way
this punch and llama he's a super duper
higher middleweight okay he's this book
is like the most beautiful higher middle
way okay
so gerstar why does he talk about names
i understand the pictures
but do you really need the names
if the seed opens in my mind
from helping poor people around the
world
and the picture comes out of the scene
and coats the
glass and creates a glass and creates a
watermelon juice why do you need the
names
why they keep saying uh
in higher middle way
why they keep saying in name only in
name only okay
name
is just a nickname for pictures okay
is just a nickname
for pictures okay it's things are not
coming from names
uh names are pictures okay
it's not the sound of name
and it's not the spelling of the name
that's creating the world
when when middleweight
says that things exist nominally
nominally means in name only
it means
things are coming from pictures in your
mind and the word name
is a nickname for picture
okay
all right so
my my seeds today
are opening
little pictures are jumping out and
making red color in my glass okay
and when i have to talk to sonam
anybody else
guess what what's in the glass you know
then you know
i don't want to say oh sudam
i'm having a mental picture of uh red
liquid
you know
i i use a nickname
i use a short name it's called mindo
i i say watermelon juice okay
and then if surname is a well-trained
buddhist nun she will say oh you mean
you having a
picture come out of your seeds
of tasty
red liquid
i say yeah yeah that's what i mean
i call it watermelon juice because
it sounds strange if you ask me what am
i drinking and i say
oh i'm drinking a picture of a red sweet
liquid that jumped out of my karma you
know
and
so we use words
to talk about pictures and then
something terrible happens
we forget
that it's a nickname and we think it's
true
we think it's real okay enemy enemy
enemy
you know attack me attack me hate me
hate me
we we use a name
and we start to forget that there's a
picture
that's behind the name and and then we
start to believe in names okay
then we call people names you're stupid
you're bad
you don't like me
and and then we get stuck in the names
okay so
okay
then he says look
who's talking by the way here
who's he or she
you guys are lucky
yeah this whole
this whole two days i i'm
we are lucky because the angel got to
talk for two days
by the way i was checking ahead to see
if we could
invite the devil back just to say
something
but i guess in this part he's busy with
his phone or something
and he doesn't talk much in in this
section okay
we'll get him next time and and we'll
try to do these angel devils uh
you know every few months or something
it's just when gesla has an extra day
uh we can have some fun and and
especially around sedona it's nice to
get together
all right
then the angel says
look
either the world is the result of big
economic political health forces
on the outside
or
things are popping up from season you
might
take you it's either one way
or it's another way
but in american english you say
you can't have it both ways okay you
can't have it you have to choose
okay
only one is true
either
nature is running the world
or huge political forces are running
either either that's true
or
pictures are jumping out of your seats
depending on how you treated people
last month
or last
okay but but the angel says look
you can't have it both ways
and i'm not just talking about the world
i'm talking about your little finger
and i'm talking about the tip of your
nose and uh
everything everything okay
i'm talking about the lines on the
screen uh on your zoom car
you know either
everything's coming from your mind or
nothing you decide okay
okay
uh
and if you decide
that there's one atom
of your life
which is not your fault okay if you
decide
that there's one atom of your life
which is not your fault
then nothing comes from the causes
okay if there's one
person in the world
who's not coming from you
then nothing's coming from you okay
and if nothing's coming from you i'll go
further
then you'd have to say nothing exists at
all okay
nothing exists at all take your choice
take your choice
everything that happens to you
is coming from how you treat other
people
or
nothing that happens to you
depends on how you treat other people
you cannot have it both ways
if you decide anything that happened to
you
is not your fault
then nothing exists at all
in the world in the universe okay got it
whoa
okay timmy one more victim here
yeah i'd like to call on someone from
vietnam her name is
ian
can you read for us please
oh yes
now my own position
on all this and does everything there is
comes from the composition
of
of course any condition and this
depending on other things
then
we can say
that everything there is
is karma
and is consequent are something i
actually experienced
and if
you stick with me
you can keep your ideas of spiritual
levels and special parts
and on this of the
show in my camp all of them are there in
my names
but there are only there in names
if
we take
the expression this isn't in reality
the way you want or to
then nothing in
the universe could ever visit at all
[Music]
uh
i wish i could speak vietnamese like
that i don't know vietnamese is very
difficult um
okay
uh
now somebody said here
you want to know my position
who's talking
yeah you hagridy
yeah the angel's still talking hey you
want to know what i think
yeah
tell us what you think
everything
comes
from causes and conditions everything
comes from dependence
that's just
never forget
never forget when the angel says
things come from causes
and conditions everything is dependent
origination
dependent origination means
being nice to other people that's all
okay
don't get
all philosophical
okay what's cause and effect
what's dependent orientation
it just means
how do you treat other people are you
nice to other people
because that's where the world is coming
from okay
how do you forget this big word
of dependent origination you know it's
it's just means
how you treat other people do you treat
other people nice
that's cause and effect okay
so the angel said look
i vote
my vote
is cause and effect my vote is
everything's coming from how you treat
other people
okay
if you agree
that everything in your life
is jumping out of your own thing
which you planted by being good or bad
to other people if you agree to that
then everything there is
is
okay if you don't agree i see about sids
then everything there is
is not
okay
okay it's very cute
if you believe seeds
then everything there is
it is
if you don't believe sins
then everything there is
is not
okay okay
it's difficult okay
uh
now she says something cute you know
she said stick with me okay in english
american english stick with me me and
sir
hey stay stay with me
you stay with me you're gonna have a
good life no
don't listen to the stupid ancient guy
you know stick with me okay
uh if you
stay believing in the scene like i say
the ah then you can go through the fire
paths of buddhism
then you can go through the 10
bodhisattva levels
only if you believe in seeds you can
have the three jewels buddha dharma
sangha okay and if you don't believe in
seeds
you cannot have the three jewels
by the way if you cannot have the three
jewels
you cannot be a buddhist not possible
okay
that that's the definition of buddhist
so only if you accept the seeds
only if you accept the angels idea
that the world is coming from you
but then then you can practice buddhism
but if not
forget buddhism okay
in my camp okay captain english means in
american english camp means uh
if you agree with my position
okay if you agree with my position
it's all there is a body suffered there
yes
can i see emptiness directly yes
can i
can i worship buddha dharma sangha yes
how
only if you understand they are coming
from you
only if you understand
they are coming out of your seats then
you can practice
buddhism but there's no buddha who
didn't come from you
there's no mixed nuts translations
that didn't come from you
you know there's no
world aci
sangha
that
tim is helping to bring together
that didn't come from you okay
and there's no other choice okay
uh either things are 100 coming from you
or zero percent coming from you there's
no compromise okay there's no
there's no percent
which is not coming from you and that
means
you cannot hate anybody
even one percent
okay
everybody's your fault okay
all the stupid people in the world
are coming from you there's a joke at
diamond mountain retreat center
at diamond mountain all the staff
you know they're very well trained
a lot of them did long retreats they're
very well trained
and they they all understand
that
when you meet a stupid person
it's coming from you okay so there's a
joke
at
diamond mountain if if the person says
i can't believe everyone around here is
so stupid you know
and then they all say yeah yeah you're
right
you're right
it's a joke it means
everybody's coming from you
if everyone says stupid around you
if everybody in your family doesn't
understand anything
uh and you criticize them
actually you are criticizing yourself
okay you're actually criticizing
yourself okay
uh let's go one more
stem
and we'll do some question and answer
all right we're gonna go to south africa
and andreas bothner
where did he go
uh you can hear me
yeah hi
we're sorry you lost bishop tutu
yes
here we go
you are darkness you are
misunderstanding and your claim is that
every single thing there is exists in
truth
you are the misunderstanding that leads
to the idea that nothing can exist
even in names
misunderstanding misunderstanding worse
than misunderstanding you are a massive
entire planet of no understanding at all
that's kind of a depressing uh
verse but okay you did it very well
uh
okay
uh usually
the angel isn't very uh
she doesn't say bad things to even
to
the devil
but here she says look you are darkness
okay you you are darkness
and darkness means uh
you know you can have a whole world
of successful economies
and uh you know smart people
but if there's no dharma
uh if if if nobody's teaching even
though you have technology
you have internet
you have
airplanes you can send rockets every day
up to the moon
but if you don't understand about seeds
then you are living in a primitive
society okay
it's very interesting
okay
so
you we say oh gesture we are not cavemen
you know we we are not living in caves
we are not hitting each other with rocks
you know
we don't kill every person we can find
because they might have some food you
know we are civilized
and we are advanced
and we have technology you know
this is the first generation
in 50 000 years
that i can do a zoom call
[Music]
all over the world and somebody from
south africa
and somebody from vietnam
and somebody from germany
can all meet together you know this is a
wonderful
world and the angel says no
it's just darkness okay
it's worse than the cavemen times
if you don't have dharma okay if you
don't have dharma
and i worry about it a lot you know i i
really worry about it a lot
that uh
and and that's why i keep talking about
these books i'm not trying to sell books
okay we lose money on the books i'm
sorry
uh i'm not trying to sell the books
but the world is a dark place
uh the world is like in a permanent
nighttime
and if there's one book
that talks about seas
then that's like the sun in this world
and and that the normal sun it doesn't
matter
you know that the sun comes up or the
sun goes down
still it's darkness okay
whether the sun is up
or whether the sun is down
without this
thing's
knowledge then this world is dark
this this world is in a permanent time
okay and she's talking to him you know
if if we run the world
like you say you know if if we do normal
politics and
economics and
you know normal science
then really this is a dark world this
world is dark okay and all the people
are blind
and just a
permanent nighttime
and people are
hurting each other all the time okay so
uh
she she's criticizing him
you know if we listen to you
and we think anything is coming from
itself
and if we don't believe everything is
coming from me
like in the kitchen
then truly this is a dark world it
doesn't matter you have internet or you
have cell phone or you have airplane
or you have rocket ship you are
primitive you are caveman
and you are killing each other okay with
sticks and rocks
okay you are the same okay
okay
then if we listen to you
then nothing can exist okay every
not only the world is dark
and not only people are hurting each
other
but if we follow your thinking
then actually this world doesn't even
exist it's it's not the world is dark
or there's a permanent nighttime in this
world if we follow your idea
that the world is coming this way
then there's no world
to be dark also
nothing okay
last thing
uh
the worst thing about you mr devil
is you don't understand how bad you are
okay you don't even understand
where misunderstanding comes from okay
in your system
mr
devil you don't even understand
where did
misunderstanding come from you even
misunderstand
misunderstanding okay if i ask you
hey why you didn't understand the pen 10
years ago
you know why you didn't understand the
pen 20 years ago
you said i didn't know nobody taught me
ah
now you misunderstand misunderstanding
okay it's not nobody taught you
is that you didn't share
your understanding with other people
so you didn't meet anybody to depend
you don't even understand why you don't
understand
[Music]
you don't even understand why you don't
understand so she's getting frustrated
and and then she says you know you are
you are a huge planet
you are the whole earth
with people eight billion people walking
on it
and only a few thousand understand where
the world is coming from okay 8 billion
people
are walking in
in darkness
and a few people understand the pin okay
so
that's your job you guys every country
every every country's people
you gotta
share the
10 story the light okay
just people love to talk about their
husband in the kitchen okay just try and
uh it really helps people a lot it makes
the world a better place if one person
out of a million
understands
where the husband's coming from
that changes the world that changes the
whole balance of the world
and suddenly peace will start to happen
and more more prosperity
and more happiness
if just one person in a million
understands seeds
then it makes a big difference in the
world because their ideas will start to
spread and spread and spread
okay tim you got any questions
we
you're on the go until nine o'clock
whoa
okay
i mean we could do questions or if you
want to teach some more or
something do some more i thought it was
8 30 i'm sorry okay
okay here we go
you have another meter
i do
um
let's go over to spain piagras
you like to read
hi pia
microphone
sorry
hello
hi
good to see you pay lip service to the
idea that
you pay lip
service to the idea that things are
deceptive
but law
if something is deceptive
then
its own causes and conditions too
you keep saying instead that things can
exist without relaying anything else
what you are really saying then is that
there is no such thing as a distinctive
reality
okay cool
cool thank you
long time no see
uh
this is the
idea of uh thank you
illusion okay you can say maya
and uh it's a very famous idea
in buddhism you know they're always
talking about illusion and illusion
maya
and it's i don't know it's a very sexy
word everybody likes it i don't know why
but what's the real illusion
and it sometimes it's called deceptive
in in buddhist uh philosophy
it's called deceptive
hey who can tell me the tibetan word tim
deceptive reality
uh
it's very easy
what does it mean illusion
it mean a dualistic
perception what's it mean
it's very simple
when you go in the kitchen
and the husband calls you stupid
and you didn't say anything yet he's
just attacked you
you didn't say anything yet and he
attacked you you know
it looks like
he had a bad day
or
he didn't get good sleep last night
he had too much traffic on the way home
he's in a bad mood
it looks like
the problem
is
his bad mood okay in english
when you say it looks like
that's deceptive
and that's maya
and that's illusion okay it looks like
your husband is upset today
because something went wrong in his job
or his boss yelled at him or something
like that it looks like that that's
called deceptive reality
well what's the truth gestala
well the truth is you were yelling at
your kids last week
and you heard your yelling came from
here to here
and it made a impression on your mind
and then
that became a karmic theme and that's
that's why your husband is yelling today
okay it's always your fault okay
so what's this
it means the world is lying to you all
day
okay the world is lying to you
all day you know oh look
there's this political problem why
oh this country did that and this
country did that
oh
i see
and what's true
is that you were unfriendly to somebody
else or you split up other people okay
the cause of seeing
countries hurt each other
one of the big causes is i don't know
why but we like to split up other people
who are friends
or who who who like each other i don't
know why we like to split them up but we
say oh you know
we we feel unhappy that other people are
happy it's a strange thing okay
so
it looks like
the world
is is happening because of all these big
forces in the world but actually
that's an illusion it's it's coming from
us so
don't think uh
buddhism is saying
oh look the cup's not real
oh look the the iphone's
not real you know don't don't believe it
that's not what buddhism is saying
that's not illusion
this is real okay
i i'll hit you on the head with it it
will make a real bump
but
it's real okay
it's really coming from you
okay it's not real the way it looks like
okay
so
by the way i'll give a hundred dollars
if kesla hit gesla on the head pretty
hard with the cell phone
okay uh and if geshe like get a bump
uh on his air conditioning part
[Music]
did the bum come from the phone
hundred dollar question did the bump
come from the phone no
who said no
what was haggerty
come on haggerty let's why not
based on what you just explained it'd be
impossible it must be coming from
something you've done towards something
someone else you must have heard
good
good you know it seems very
simple
and it it seems very kind of crazy
but if i hit my head on the
air conditioning part
with the cell phone
and if a bum
comes out
the bump didn't come from the cell phone
the cell phone came from my seat
moving the cell phone came from my sleep
and then the bump came from my seat but
the bomb didn't come from the cell phone
okay it's very difficult to understand
okay
if i hit my head on
with the phone
and then a bum comes from my
on my head
the phone is coming from my seats
the movement is coming from my seats
and the bump is coming from my seats
and there's no connection
between the phone and the bump whoa
okay there's no connection that's not
causing effect
okay you hit your head with the phone
you know just geisha goes to the college
later today
tim says oh geshe-la you got a bump on
your head what happened
i think geisha will say i hit my head
with the phone you know
then tim will say gesture that's not how
you got the bomb
the phone didn't make the bump that's an
illusion
the seed made the phone
the seed made the gum
and the seed made the bump
bump bump no connection no connection
that the phone
not connected to the bottom
not connected to the left okay they are
not connecting
each one is coming up separately from
different seeds that's all it's very
interesting
it's all an illusion
everything you try to do
to be happy
is mistaken everything everything
to to to try to drink the watermelon
juice
to to not be thirsty is a mistake
you should give it to somebody okay
whoa
[Music]
all right tim we can can we do some more
yeah surely you gotta keep
you gotta keep me in the truck here
all right
where did they go i just saw them oh i i
want to we're not going to have this
person read but i want to spotlight
somebody
elena with shanti
oh wow paul
wow look at shanti oh my gosh
wow
he's gonna be bigger than you in about
two weeks i think
i know
it's very beautiful
okay
okay i hope everything's going well i
saw a beautiful photograph um
apache was holding shanti and and they
are both yawning at the same time it was
very beautiful
congratulations
thank you
all right so we haven't
we have another shanti on here who's
in gainesville florida i think they
disappear they are
let's let's add them so this is shanti
in gainesville florida yay gainesville
oh do you want a review sure i forgot i
had my camera on so that was uh an offer
right
yeah you made a mistake you got to turn
off the camera when it's time
no that's great we're glad to be here
yeah good day
in general terms we can say that if we
stick to your system
nothing could ever die
and more particularly
we'd have to say that nothing could ever
be born at all
so now suppose that that a pleasure
being
passes away and is born as one of their
lesser cousins
back when they had the body and mind of
a pleasure being
they looked at those and said that's me
now according to you that belief in a
true existence would not have changed
and so now
they're looking at the body and mind of
the lesser cousin
and thinking now that's me
you'd have two that's me's
coming together in a single place in
time
of course no such thing is possible
but the problem that it would have to be
is a necessary consequence of this
belief of yours
that things could exist in truth
so tell me then what's really going to
happen when those two things come
together
okay
uh
you picked a hard one
you picked a really hard one and i'm
having i always have a hard time with
all of this
it's okay but uh
i i tell you myself uh it used to put me
to sleep
and if i couldn't sleep
i would get this book and i would try to
read it
and i would fall asleep immediately and
it's better than
sleeping medicine you know
i i will just
open up this book and try to read one
page
i i remember uh when i was in the
monastery if i have trouble sleeping
uh i will this book i will open it and i
will try to read a page
and
put me to sleep right away and and i
think
in this lineage in this tradition
uh
we train our mind to be tough you know
and it it
it takes the years you know you have to
keep
fighting with things you don't
understand and then your mind gets
strong
and so and there's a joke some kappa
he never uh
his commentaries are funny
his commentaries on the ancient books
are funny
because he always skips the easy part
he never
writes about the easy part
he just goes to the yeah it's a copper
book
i'm very proud of this book uh that
finally finished it
it took about 15 years uh but he he
always skips the easy part and
and i
and we just finished that dci uh
advanced level the first advanced level
and it's about uh problem solving how to
solve problems and
and it's a kind of a
discipline
that you go for the tough problems first
and uh you start to enjoy them
you know
so anyway
in this book uh
you if you don't understand something or
it makes you sleepy
then keep coming back keep coming back
to it because something valuable is
there
if you understand it right away i have
to say probably it's not that valuable
okay
and if it takes some time to understand
it
then uh probably there's something
valuable there okay so
the angel says to the devil
uh
you know if we kick to your system
and things are coming from the outside
then nothing could die
and
nothing could ever be born okay
so it means uh your car couldn't break
and you couldn't buy a new car
if the car's not coming from you
and you have to think about it i'll say
it again
if your car is not coming from you
it could never break
and if
if it did break
you could never buy a new car
if it's not coming from you okay my
friends uh
stanley and allison they bought a new
car they bought a new old car
this week
and
so they have a new car right
but we have to say
the reason they got a new car
is that they gave rides to other people
they were generous
in the past and and they helped other
people
to get to where they wanted to go
and i know they did do that and that's
what created the new car but
if you don't understand scenes
and you think you can get a new car
then then you're crazy then you're crazy
if you think
you can get a new car
without helping other people
to get where they want to go
then that's crazy okay that's what the
angel is saying to the devil
and now she says
let's talk about new car
meaning your body after you die okay so
let's
she wants to take the conversation
back to the
to the deva to the like we call pleasure
being right uh she wants to take the
conversation
back to where she started this
they were talking about
people
who did good things for other people
but they didn't understand seats they
just had a habit
to do good things or their mom told them
to do good things
or the church told them to do good
things
but they didn't really understand what
they are doing
then they will get good results they
will beautiful things will happen to
them
for example when they die
they can go to a nice place you know for
a while okay
so
now he says
let's talk about
this kind of people
who do good things for other people
but they don't really understand seeds
they just do good things because their
mom told them to do it
or their teachers told them to do it but
they don't understand seeds really so
they will have a
temporary good life
they will burn up those good seeds
and then those seeds will wear out and
then they will die again
and they will be born uh someplace else
okay so now uh he
he's
very interesting she's going back
to where she started she's going back
to where she started okay she said
what really happens
when you die and you go to a new world
it's not that the next world is waiting
for you it's not like um
you know you sent the construction
crew to your next live and they built
the next world
and then they invite you to come it's
not like that
[Music]
this world is coming from me
and then when i die
a new world is coming from me
and i'm not moving
from one world to another world i'm just
replacing
the last world with this world okay it's
very interesting you know
in fact when you drive to
the store
to buy
some
groceries you don't go anywhere
you don't move
your mind creates a road
your mind creates a car
your mind creates a grocery store
going from your house
to the grocery store
in the car
works exactly the same
as dying
at the end of your life
and then going to a new world okay you
don't go to a new world
your mind creates a new world and you
step into it you know it's very
interesting
uh
so he says here
okay you got these devas
uh they live a long long time
because they made good seeds
and then uh
those seeds burn up because they
they didn't understand seeds
and then they die
and then they go to a new room
but oftentimes they drop down
to a lower level
because they used up their good seats
okay so
the only ones left are the next lower
seats
so it could happen that uh
this deva
dies
and is born into the world
where their enemy lives and they become
their enemy okay it's very funny
it's like you're a white person and you
hate black people in america this kind
of thing then
you die
as a white person
then the next moment
you're born as a black person
then are you hating yourself like what
what's going on then
it's the same for deva
and then my god it's the same example
okay or i don't know you
you your country hates another country
and then you'll die in your country
and you're born in the other country
then uh
you know you're gonna hate yourself you
know
then what what's happening you know and
that's the question
okay
uh
let's say you you i don't know
you die in a
peru
and you're born in argentina okay let's
say you die in peru
and you're born in in argentina okay
which really means
your seeds were producing peru for 50
years 60 years seven years
then your seeds change
and now the seeds producing argentina
so we say you died and you were reborn
but you didn't it's just new seeds
creating the next country okay
then in this example
your new seeds create the seeds of the
country that you hate
in the last scenes
so this happens a lot okay
people die
people live in one country their whole
life
they learn to hate the people in another
country
because they're always thinking about
the people they hate in the other
country
then when they die they're born in that
country as the other people
now question
should you hate yourself or love
yourself
okay
you you you died from one country
you born in the other country that you
hate
now which one is you
how many me's are there okay
and she says look uh it's getting
complicated
you're gonna according to you
there should be two me's no why
one me is real the the me in peru is
real
not coming from you not coming from sins
and the me in argentina is also real not
coming from seeds
so now
you must be two people now if you don't
believe in the future life
if you don't believe in the past life
if you think illogically
that you can be born once but not again
that the mistake of being born can
happen once but not twice
you know
then
then there's only one me okay
but if your seeds create another you
then which you are you okay which you
are you you now you don't have to
believe
in the past life and future life forget
it
just forget it
okay don't worry about it
i guess i don't accept a future life
okay that's okay do you accept tomorrow
do you accept that you will be here
tomorrow yes
uh
where's that person come from
oh gesla
the person tomorrow
it comes from the person today
okay
the person tomorrow
it comes from the person today
and then we say well what if it comes
from seeds
if the person today
comes from seeds
and then the person tomorrow
comes from seeds okay
what if the seeds change
and today person
becomes tomorrow person what if it works
like that if it doesn't work like that
then there's one person today
and there's another person tomorrow
which one are you
which one are you okay if if it's not
seeds
if seeds are not producing today
and if seeds are not producing tomorrow
and if today's me is a real me
not coming from seeds
and if tomorrow's me is a real me
then which me are you
which me are you are you today me or
tomorrow me which are you
okay
and we say
you can only move from today to tomorrow
when the seeds change when the seeds
produce
tomorrow
then the seeds from yesterday wore out
then you can go from today to tomorrow
there's no other person
there's no other person that's how you
go from today to tomorrow
so you can say
i don't know after i finish this talk i
have to go to the college
it's about 45 minute drive
uh according to this idea
my seeds create my house
and my seeds create michael sitting in
the house
and then those seats finish
and then new seats create a car
and new seats create a road
and then new seats create the college
and
and then new seats create michael
sitting in the college okay
and that's how michael goes to the
college michael does not get in a car
and go to the college
in in you know 15 minutes or something
michael it does not true
steve start creating michael at home
seats are creating michael in the car
and seeds are creating michael at the
college and that's how michael goes to
the college there's no going you cannot
go
okay i think we are gonna
leave the next verse tim let's do some
question and answer because the next
verse is kind of depressing okay
it's about jealousy
i think we should leave it with a good
one with a good verse okay
you guys got any questions
yes we do
um so geshla this is uh several people
asked this question in various forms
recently so i'm going to summarize it
hopefully more people will get their
questions answered
so i have my own seeds
and everything is coming from me
and there seems to be other people out
there
that have their own seeds as well
right so they have their own experiences
they suffer
in their own ways you know
it seems like they're collecting karma
and experiencing it separate from myself
and then we say hey this is coming from
me too
right
yes so how can we think about this
because it does seem like people have
other
have their own separate entirely
separate seeds
yet we also say it comes from me too how
can we think about this
yeah that's a great question and i i you
know
i'm 69 years old i'm worrying about
these questions for 50 years
that's why i'm teaching the class sorry
all the questions you are asking
i had those questions before
and uh it's a great question and and i
struggled
with this question i think i'm lucky
because i was not born as a buddhist and
i was not born in a buddhist country
so none of my buddhism is coming from my
parents or
or my country or my culture all of my
buddhism
is coming from teachers and from great
books and
so i
i have all the questions that you're
asking
uh
i've had those questions i had the same
questions
and i struggled for many years you know
so about this question
i like to think of it as a big bubble
you know
and
my seeds
are creating right now you know i i see
a mountains and sky and
you know
it's a it's a beautiful i never
oh
[Music]
anyway i live on a mountain
and um
i'm i'm seeing a whole beautiful
desert and a mountain and
blue sky
and that's my bubble okay that's coming
from my seat
and then uh you have your own bubble you
know you you have against
florida
bubble
you know
and uh
it's creating florida
around you you know hi bubble
probably there's an ocean i'd like to
borrow
and then uh
i have my desert bubble
and
i like to think it's like those um
space man helmets you know
and uh recently i was reading about this
famous russian
cosmonaut called the yuri gagarin
and
wow his helmet the first helmet ever
you know the first space helmet
uh from the soviet union this big
uh helmet and and i thought wow that's
cool
like uh those russian scientists
invented
uh this helmet
and people still using it you know so
you can think of your
seeds opening
and creating uh your own space helmet
you know like virtual reality
and then sometimes
you can talk to another person
and you you touch your helmets together
you know
so your bubble uh touches my bubble
you know and where it touches
we can have conversation you know
yours is creating some words
and my seeds creating some words and
then we can have some uh communication
and communication means
uh
your seeds are creating
and my seeds are creating
sounds
uh to hear your words
at the same time okay so our
our
helmets
are bubbles they touch each other
and then uh gestala can talk on the zoom
and you guys can ask a question on the
zoom
so
you can think of it that way and it's
it's correct it's actually pretty
correct
uh there's a kind of
beautiful
spiritual practice you can do
which is a tradition it's an ancient
tradition
and that's to
try to understand
that maybe the people around you
are having a completely different bubble
at the same time okay so
sometimes
just sit and think
you don't really know
you can sit
with another person
you could even enjoy uh breakfast
together
but you don't really know
how are they experiencing the world and
there's a tradition
to do a special meditation
during the day time
and just imagine
that these other people are already
cleaned their seeds completely okay the
people around you
they are
they are seeing paradise
you know
you're seeing uh
you know normal life normal work
then maybe the person next to you
has a different
helmet maybe they have a different
bubble you know it's
it's very possible
there must be people in the world okay
this this teaching survived for two and
a half thousand years
that's a hundred generations
uh this book this book uh the mixed nuts
just finished this book is a
hundred generations ago this book is is
two and a half thousand years old
people don't keep books
and people don't pass those books on to
the next generation
if they don't work you see the books
that don't work died already
the books that don't work are gone
already you know
uh if a book survives
for here's the little one by the way
gina made this one diamond cutter sutra
very beautiful
fits in your hand
uh if this book survive
for two and a half thousand years
it means it helps somebody and and
somebody translated it again
and somebody published it again
and
you know
uh
rosa
made the ebook again
and so
if these books
survive in the world
for 2 000 years
it must be
it worked for somebody
okay it must be uh
there are people in the world
who already finished the paradise
and their their seeds are already
producing a self
reproducing paradise
okay
there must be people like that
and their bubble must be different from
our bubble so
will there come a time somebody asked my
teacher
i remember it was in new york
uh at a place called mcdougall street
and and somebody asked my teacher
does it ever happen that we all
make perfect seeds together
at the same time does it ever happen in
the future
that everybody's a space helmet is the
same one
and we're all sharing uh the same world
you know same perfect world
you know and he said yeah that's mandala
that's called mandala you know that's
called
perfect world when you do teaching
you offers
when you offer mandala
it means
at some time everybody's helmet
will become the same helmet and and we
will all see each other
as buddhas and
then he he's i'll never forget the last
word he said
he said uh what happens did you know
they were all like uh i don't know
what happens then you know
he says what do you think happens then
and we're all like i don't know you know
what he says oh those
those buddhas they just retire
they all retire
you know they you got to your heaven
i got to my heaven
we're creating the same heaven together
he said what do you think they all
retire
and we said i don't know it doesn't
sound like buddha should retire
it sounds a little weird gesla he said
you're right
he said they just have fun together you
know they just enjoy
that bubbles all day together you know
and
they don't retire they just have fun
together that's the future
okay timothy
grandpa has to go teach another class